You have a bunch of animation clips representing one specific action, but with different styles
or different moods, and you want to be able to blend those styles and moods doing those
actions.
Hi, I'm Jerome, and today we'll be looking at the verb and adverb multidimensional motion
blending using radial basis functions, a paper from 1999.
So what the paper says is that you will have your animations that will have actions and
they will call them verbs.
So you have the idle, walking, crouching and all that kind of stuff.
And then you will have adverbs on top of them representing the style or the mood so you
could be happy, sad, or even leaning left, leaning right, turning left, turning right.
All of those will be adverbs and you can have as many adverbs as you want and you will
to be able to blend all those animations together by just saying I want to have my walking verb
with a leaning right happy animations for instance. So how they would do this first thing I would do
is that I will import all the libraries I need and I will import my character I will extract the
skeleton you will see later why so basically I turn my skeleton into quaternions and positions
because that's what I will be working with, creating a little mesh that allow me to display
stuff on the ground. And then this is finally all the animations I want to use in my case.
So I will not have moods as happy, sad and aghast stuff. What I will have is walking
animations and I will have the walking with turning left, walking turning right, and two
different styles, one with small steps and one doing bigger steps. So that's the animations I
I would have in my case, and this is all the animations
I will be using as one verb.
So the verb is walking, and all of those are adverbs.
So it's all the turning lefts, all the examples for turnings,
all the examples for the type of steps.
So this is all the animations I want to use.
Now that I have all the animations I want to use,
and I know what the adverbs I will be using,
We can start to look at the paper to see exactly how it works.
And so for them, they said that you
will have a lot of different motions.
And then they represent the motions basically
as this one saying that you have a motion itself,
a set of degrees of freedom.
So for us, it will be the rotations
in translation of every bones.
For them, I think that because they talk about degrees of freedom as a really low level,
it's probably just the rotations as Euler angle, you know, one angle for the elbow,
three angles for the wrists and shoulders and that kind of stuff.
So they have the exact degrees of freedom.
I would be working in quaternions and I would stay inside of quaternions,
which means now that my degrees of freedom is basically the number of bones
I would have multiplied by seven because I have w x y z for each quaternions and x y z for each
translate. So a bit heavier, not what they had in their mind, but it would work just the same way
for us. So the way they encode the data when they do animations, they talk about the degrees of
freedom. For them, any animations is actually encoded inside of a uniform cubic B spline. So
So I recommend watching the uniform cubic B-spline videos
I did earlier.
So you have a number of control points for the entire animation,
and that's allowed you to get the animation back.
Now, what is really interesting in this case,
what I said is basically every animation's
inside of your ad-vab.
So you can see that my animations have different lengths
and different timing, but they will all be encoded
with the same number of control points.
So for the number of control points,
you decide empirically how many you want of them
for all of your animations,
and then you will use the same number.
So I will not encode my animation
as uniform cubic B-spline just yet,
because I have a lot of other stuff to do
before I will be able to do this.
First thing first, they do a time warping of the animations to get into what they call
the canonical form.
And basically the idea behind this is to realize that all of animations have different timings
and different lengths, and we want to re-encode them to be all of the same length.
So the generic timing for them will be instead of saying I have 30 frames or 60 frames of
animations, it just timing goes between 0 and 1 as a parametric functions. My animations goes
between 0 and 1 and that's it. So we will stretch and squash the timing, so we will basically do
time warps as in the paper, the time warping paper. And on top of this, we want to make sure that
everything inside of each animations
have the same timing reference.
So basically the beginning of the animations at time one,
the end of the animation is at time zero, sorry,
the end of the animations at time one.
And then in my case, because it's a working animation,
I can decide that I want to detect
when the foot hits the ground
and when it's lift the ground.
So all my animations start with the left foot going down.
left foot going down.
So I will have a time zero at the beginning of animations
and then when the left foot hits the ground
is time zero point two, for instance,
then the right legs go up, that's time zero point four
and then it goes down time point six
and then this one goes up time point eight
and then end of the animation is time one.
So we will compute the different timing
for all of our animations this way.
So what I do is this for the canonical form,
I've already pre-computed all the values.
So you can see my first animations,
the different timing I have inside of my real animation
is that at frame zero, it starts.
Then at frame seven, I get my first contact,
11, 23, 27, 32.
So I get all of those.
And basically to do this,
how they do it in the paper is all done by hands manually.
So it's a manual processor.
I had this little window that's allowed me
to create those information.
So you could see my animation zero,
the value is from zero seven.
So I know that frame at frame seven,
what I have is the contact of my right foot.
At frame 11 is when I decided that
when the contact from the left foot doesn't exist anymore,
then I will be frame 23.
That's when the contact will reopen.
there. 23, I get the contact, 27, I don't have the contact anymore and so on and so on.
And you do this for all of your animations. So it's a manual process. It is tricky to get
right and that's usually why the blending might be a bit off when you try to blend all the info
because contact will not be exactly the same on every animations. But it's a manual process,
you have to do it for every animations, but I have done it.
What I would do on top of this, because all those animations
come from motion captures, and I just
picked a clip into motion capture.
It's not an animation that done by hand,
which has nice cycles.
I need to make those animation loop properly
so I could be able to use those animations
because walking animations, I want
to be able to make the character walk after it.
So I will make the animation loop.
And to do this, basically, the only thing I do
is that I take the first frame and the last frame.
I take the difference between the two frames
when I'm here with the offsets.
And now that you know how much arrows basically you
have with the last frame to be exactly the same as the first
frame, you just propagate that error slowly
through time during your animation.
So if I have an animation that says I have 100 frames,
I would say that frame 0 is just my frame 0.
at frame one is frame one plus 1% of the error.
Frame two is frame two plus 2% of the error.
So on and then at the end is frame 100
with 100% of the error on top.
And so I get the exact same pose.
So you do this in the local space of all your bones.
And at the same time, if you just do this,
basically your feet will start to slide, unfortunately.
So what I do is that I also compute
where the foot would be at the end of the animations
after I corrected it.
So I get the first frame, I know where the positions are
and at the end, I modify that pose
and I compute where the foot would be.
And now that I know this, I basically make sure
that I will only change, apply that fixing,
that correction that I did on the entire animations.
I will only do it when the feet are going up and going down.
So it starts from where it was before doing any fixes.
And during the fly, it will reach directly
where it's supposed to be at the end of the corrections.
So that's the local offsets.
And then I get the stuff when I compute the global version
of the left foot and the right foot.
And I'm just using the timing because I know exactly
by the timings, I know when the feet are hitting the ground
so I can just use that information from the timing
I computed before.
This is why I'm doing the looping now basically.
And now I can just compute the looping animations
for all my animations.
And what I have is these animations.
So basically you won't see a lot of difference,
but if I go on spot, you see now that I have a looping
animations for all of those, and I do loop properly,
and everything is fine now.
Now I have my looping animations that works properly,
but what I need is to have them encoded as generic time,
say going between zero and one,
instead of having the number of frames as you wanted,
that's I had before.
And so what I will do is that I will warp my animations
using the timing I did
to make it, to warp it using the time warps basically.
And because I'm using data at this point,
I cannot just say between zero and one
and not having any informations.
The timing will be between zero and one,
but then I need to have the intermediate values
and decide how many intermediate values I want to have
in to encode my data to be able to work with.
And what I would do is I would say that I'd go
for 400 frames, which is a lot bigger
than my original animations.
My original animations were only 30 frames
or a maximum 60 frames.
So now I have an animation that will be
with a lot more data when I'm doing this,
but it's because the time what sometimes will slow down
a piece of the animations,
and sometimes it will accelerate a piece of the animations.
And I want to make sure that when it accelerates,
I actually have enough data in between,
I don't want to have only suddenly zero or two frames in between because it
means nothing in data when I would try to compute the cubic bezier so I grow my
animation so I know that I have something that will have enough data so
the warping is just this it takes every range that I have inside of my time
warping functions and it will just scale all those range properly and it does it
linearly. So the paper was actually doing the time warp linearly between all the values.
So I do the same, I will just stretch each piece of the animations linearly the same way.
And what I would do on top, so what I've done this for, see now my new animations will be
400 frames long. I have six values, so it means that I actually have 80 frames between each of
my ranges. So I compute the the quaternions, all the quaternions, all the positions.
I normalize my quaternions now because I did just linear interpolations without any stuff.
And what is important for me now here is because I'm not working in Euler angle
or any other representations, I'm actually working in quaternion space.
which means that when I would try to blend quaternions together, I need to make sure that
they are exactly in the same quadrant. You know that quaternions have a double cover,
meaning that the quaternion and the inverse of the quaternion represent the same 3D rotation.
So if, for instance, finally you try to blend together one quaternion and it's inverse,
the rotation between will probably do a 360 and that kind of stuff and I don't want this I want
to be able to just blend as if it was the closest values and the simplest way to do it is actually
to make sure that every quaternions you have inside your animation would be in the same quadrant
as the bind pose of your skeleton. So it has the advantage of saying that everything stays
around the bind pose of the animations, meaning that any values that you try to blend together will
always stay naturally inside of what the bone is supposed to do. So even if I have a value that
it might be negative or positive, something really close, it would always do the right
rotations. It would never try to do the opposite and go in the opposite directions,
because I've made every quaternion be
closest as possible as the bind pose, let's say.
So that's what I'm doing here. I'm checking that the angle between
my animations and the bind pose is in the same quadrant and if they're not
I'm just inverting those so all the quaternions are in the bind pose
quadrant. So now that I have done this, what I have
is all my animations now have exactly all the same length.
They are all 400 frames long.
That's supposed to be just the timing between zero and one.
And I can display those animations.
And then you could see that what happens is that now everything
is a lot slower.
But it slows down some steps and accelerates
just to make sure that if I post these animations,
I can pick any specific frame.
For instance, I'm passing.
So my left foot is passing the right foot.
And if I check any other animations,
I would be in the same at the same time
with exactly at the passing stage of any style.
So, and you could see for this one,
this one actually slows down
and then will really slow down at this time.
And then we'll have to reaccelerate quickly
because the timing of those animations is really different.
So that's what the time warp was used for,
so make sure that all the informations
hit at the same time.
And now that I have all my animations
into the canonical form,
so they all have the same length,
they all have the same frame,
all the frames presenting the same data,
I can actually turn them into a uniform cubic Bezier.
And to do this, I would just do the minimize functions
to find the best uniform cubic Bezier I can find
to cover the animation curves.
So I'm using the minimize functions
and I try to find out the minimum error.
And the number of control points you choose,
So the one that you decide how many control points
that controls one animations, it's something you choose.
And in this case, I will just pick 23 control points.
So I will actually now have 23 control points
for each of my curves when I do this.
So this is the functions to convert.
And this one actually is converting all the animations.
So what I will have is the quaternion and positions
for all my animations,
for the 23 control points for each bones
and then for each curves inside of those.
So the WXYZ and the XYZ of the positions.
So that's a lot of different curves
that I would be converting.
It would take a bit of time.
I'm coming back when it's done.
So now what we have is not an animations in terms of frames,
frames but just animation in terms of those control points. So the only thing I have in
the animations are those control points here and that's actually enough to rebuild the curve.
And you can see that the blue one is the reconstructed curves and the little dashed one
are the original data. So that's for one of the animations for the heaps and the quaternions
X values in this case, so that's the one I've picked to display this stuff, but it works
for all of the curves I have inside of the systems.
And I can show that we could actually render the animation using this.
So now I'm not replaying the animation itself, I'm playing the animations that was encoded
in uniform cubic B-spline.
And it plays at the right speed,
because on top of this I'm not only just computing,
recomputing the animation,
so you could see I get the B-spline functions
that allow me to take a specific set of control points
and rebuild the curves.
So that's the functions you have from the other video.
So I'm rebuilding all the quaternions
and all the positions.
And I'm going to renormalize my cotonians, of course,
because they are completely unnormalized.
Now, I did reconstruct curves separately,
so I need to renormalize my cotonians.
And on top of this, I'm converting back the generic time.
The delta time I want to play, because I
want to move to the next real frame in real time.
But then I need to find what it means inside of the generic time
to move those values.
So you need to say, OK, I'm moving one frame forward.
How many frames does that represent?
How many times does it represent in the generic time?
Is it 0.1, 0.2, and so on, and so on?
So you have to go through the timings,
find what were the different timings for the different time
and play at the right frames so this is what I'm doing here I'm finding back
inside the generic time what is my values and now that I have my generic
time I can just request that correct frames inside of my animations and that
gives me basically this and the quantity to play back any of the
animations using the cubic B-spline and we will finally be able to actually build our verb with
all of this. Now I have all my animations in the canonical form and encoded as a bunch of control
points for uniform cubic B-spline not animation data itself anymore and I can go through the verb
construction one and to build those you actually use that was the purpose of
this paper is to use the radial basis functions and for each degrees of freedom
so that's the value that you will have to to compute except they use b because
that's one of the control points of the uniform B spline. So for each of those control points now
what you will have to do is to compute radial basis functions and a linear approximation. I will
not go through the mathematics on how they compute all those informations because I've done the other
videos that represent the mathematics for it. Just watch that one and you will have heavy
introductions to how they computed that specific coefficients, but basically we
need to find the coefficients for the radial basis functions and the
coefficients for the linear approximations for every, basically for
every control point. So that will be for every degrees of freedom, for every
animations and for every control points of every curves.
That's a lot of different coefficients we have to compute.
And on top of it, they do it for every control points to be able to blend those control points
together.
But they do it also for the timing.
of our animations have time warps and we decided that the time warps was in this case always defined
by six different values because the you know the beginning the first the first foot on the ground
the second left ground left and so on so that's my six time values inside of a time warp and basically
we will do the same thing we will use that same radial basis functions but with the timing this
time we will have for every animations for every of those six values we will have a radial basis
function and that's what this class is doing it basically allows us to give a bunch of adverbs
with examples, build all the information we want and then fit a specific curve through it so we
will be able to fit any of our control points animations or we'll be able to fit the timings
and that kind of stuff and that returns the coefficients we want to use and then we could
actually interpolate using those coefficients so that's what this class is doing and what I would
do is just this I will now actually make real adverbs because so far I'm talking about the
motions that have different directions and examples but I haven't encoded what for me
that represents inside of the adverb space and that's what I would do here. I would create
the adverb space and basically for me it's to the adverb space. The first one is how much left or
right I have inside of that animations. And the second part is the style. For the angle,
I'm doing something fairly simple. I take the first frame and then I take the last frame and I
check what angle I have between those. And that gives me the advanced values at the angle,
the amount of rotations I had at the end of the animation. And the second one is the style.
and now I will encode it manually because I know which animations have which style.
So basically all the the seven first animations have the small steps one
and then the other animations have the biggest steps one the five one
I have the the second style so two style and the angle of rotations.
And so now that I have the adverbs I can actually create my radial basis functions
and then I will start to be able to fit to get all the coefficients I need. So
what I would do is that I will fit one by one because it would be easier to
just see exactly what I'm fitting than trying to fit a multi-dimensional
timings and all kind of stuff that I don't want to to fight against swizzling
the animations, the data and that kind of stuff. So I have the timing, the linear
Timing coefficients and the radial timing coefficients. It's basically the six values
I had inside of a timing and then I get the three values for the linear coefficients because that's
The adverbs size plus one
And then the 12 different values because I have 12 different
examples animations and I compute so the timing I fit the timing all of them
I do the same for every point cloud every
uniform-basic control points of any bones of all the degrees of freedom of each
bone. So basically, you know, my 23 points, every bones in the characters, the WXYZ
of the quaternions, XYZ of the positions, and then again the three, the three and
12 for the linear and radial. And now that I have all those coefficients, I
I will be able to use those coefficients
to actually play my animation
and blend the different values.
So one thing I haven't done inside of these implementations
is actually what they call the verb graph.
So basically what we have is the fact that
we have one action, which is the walking actions
and I have a bunch of adverbs.
say the verb is working, my adverbs is all my style and rotations, and then normally you will
build a graph of verbs, you will be able to do from idle, go to walk and then maybe crouch or
sit and that kind of stuff, and all of those verbs will have adverbs and all of those, and
basically you build a graph of verbs and you make transitions between the the different verbs.
I haven't done this part because we've done this when we we've done the motion
graph it's basically the same thing except that instead of a verb you have
a complete verb and adverbs but then you have transitions between those verbs
and you blend the results between the verbs so nothing really fancy in the
verb graph itself. What I'm more interesting in is how they evaluate
the adverbs and so this is how you what you have to compute. Now to compute
your animations when you have the different adverbs and you want to
blend them together the first thing is to interpolate all the timings you know
we've decided that each animations had a time warps and they all have different
time warps. And then we build the coefficients for the different time warps. So we would
blend together all those different time warps to find how we should normally time warp the
blended results. So now we have to compute the blended time warped, let's say.
And once you've done this, you could convert it into the generic time to know where you want to
pick inside of all our canonical form animations. And give us the T. Then for every degree of freedom,
for every control points,
we need to blend those control points together.
So all the first control points
of every degrees of freedom together,
all the second control points
of all the degrees of freedom together,
and so on, and so on.
So it's per frame, per control points,
per degrees of freedom.
And then once you've done this, we could actually evaluate the uniform cubic Bezier because
we've blended the control points of the cubic Bezier and then we could evaluate that cubic
Bezier and we have our animation.
If we had to compute all of that at every frame, that would be a lot of things to compute.
Instead, what we could see is that at any time when we try to evaluate the uniform cubic
B-spline, we don't need to evaluate every control point.
We're just interested in the four control points that are useful to be able to compute
our values.
That's what I'm showing here, it's how we could, you know, if my values can go between
0 and 1, which is my generic time. At any point, if I need to compute the values itself, I only
need to evaluate those four control points. I don't need to evaluate the 23 of them, just the four
relevant control points. And that's what I would do. I will only evaluate those fours.
And so finally, this is the full functions. Let's see what it does. And then we can go back to
to what was computing.
So I have my character, it can now blend
with different angles and you could see
how it does blend between them
and it can blend between different mood.
And of course I could probably do this when it plays
and that will be better.
So I can walk, I can make it rotate,
you can make it rotate in the opposite directions.
It blends with all the values I want.
And I can change, for instance, my mood also.
So the mood is just changing the type of steps
and you can change the type of steps
and also the directions.
So everything has been merged together
inside of a big systems.
Now, if you watched the video about the radial basis functions
and why it was doing linear and radial basis one,
and the radial basis one it was so it could do extrapolations on top of interpolation so for
instance I don't have any example that goes further than minus something in this angle
and I can try to force it to go further it does some kind of extrapolations and then we said it
can do some kind of extrapolation but it's not that fancy you could see that extrapolation
animation kind of does something when it's not perfect.
It has a lot of issues with the looping part of the animations, but then it's even sliding.
But if I'm staying into values I have, you can just interpolate those.
Same for the mood.
If I can blend between the two, but my mood has nothing that's allowing him to turn that
big.
So I will have big issues there during the looping.
But if I stay inside of values for which I had animations, it would work a bit better.
So I can go completely changing the mood completely and it all works smoothly
So as long I have data and I'm not trying to extrapolate too much it kind of work
I can force the the foot to be on the ground
Nothing fancy here. That's why it pops like crazy. I'm just watching the timing from
the generic time to know if it I'm between a flying or
stick to the ground stuff and I
I don't even smooth in and out those constraints, I just enforce them and stop them at once
and that's why it pops like crazy.
But basically, because my animation knows when I'm supposed to lock my feet, I'll be
able to do it.
And so how this works, basically again, it's all the same stuff, I'm saving a bunch of
information because I need the characters to be able to move along, but you compute the
times.
So as I said, you interpolate the six values of the timing, you interpolate them.
So I get the computed times, the computed time warps that is the blended versions of
all the time warps.
And then when I have this, I can go and compute the generic time, thanks to those blended
time warped. And now that I have the timing I want to have, I can pick the correct four control
points I need to compute. I can compute those four different control points using the radial
basis functions. I can actually blend together all the control points that need to be blended
together. And now that I have those blended control points, I can actually evaluate
my beast plane at the specific time I need to with those four control points
I'm the only computing one time now with the four control points and then I
normalize my cotonion and that's it and everything else is just to make sure
that I can keep playing animations and it's keep moving forward that's how this
is working. So that was the, look, foot. That was the verb and adverb paper. You
could see that it's a paper from 1999 and it basically has most of the
all the features we already have specifically implemented in this case
but if we take a game engine what you will have you will have your animation
graph, which says, well, working, joking, running, and how you transition between them.
And that's the verb in this case. And then you will have inside of all those actions,
you will probably have a blend tree. That's how you decide how you blend
leaning directions or blending animation, depending on the style. So it basically is the
same as the adverb, except that all of this was computed at once trying to blend a higher
dimension systems instead of just doing a simple blend between those.
So paper from 1999 which has most of the concepts we have in game engine today
although a bit more complex in the mathematics
behind it. I hope you enjoyed it and I'll see you next time.